One of the most persistent myths in
personal finance is that owning a home
is financially superior to renting.
There are good reasons to choose either
renting or owning, but purely based on
the numbers, there's not a clear winner
on expectation. This matters because it
means that people should focus on
aspects of the decision that are
important to them rather than feeling
financial pressure to buy a place as
soon as possible. Canadian housing costs
have increased a lot over the last 20
years. That fact leads people to believe
that buying a place to live in Canada
must have been far superior to renting
and investing in stocks over that
period. That belief is wrong. I've
assembled 20 years of detailed Canadian
data to compare the analytical wealth
outcomes of renting and owning for the
20 years ending December 2024. The
results will blow your mind. I'm Ben
Felix, chief investment officer at PWL
Capital, and I'm going to show you with
real numbers that renting a place to
live has not been a bad financial
decision in Canada for the last 20
years.
[Music]
In past videos, I have shown that
renting and owning are financially
comparable based on projections built on
assumptions about things like property
tax rates, the rate of return on real
estate and stocks, and inflation. I
think those projections and their
underlying assumptions are reasonable,
but they're not reality. In this video,
I'm going to use actual historical data
for 12 Canadian cities to show the same
thing. I'll be honest, I was surprised
by the results. I was expecting renting
to look terrible, and it actually looks
great. Before you tell me I'm wrong,
please watch the video. I will walk
through my data, assumptions, and
results in detail. There's a narrative
that renting has been a mistake in
Canada in recent history due to rising
property values. But as you'll see, the
results across the country have been
mixed both by geography and by time
period with renting making a very strong
showing most of the time, even in cities
like Toronto. I used data for apartments
due to data quality and availability for
the 20 years ending December 2024. I
looked at that full period and the four
non-over overlapping 5-year sub periods
for each city. In seven of the 12
cities, the renter accumulates more
wealth than the owner over the full
period. And the renter comes out ahead
in 71% of the 48 5-year sub periods
across all cities. That may seem
surprising, but one issue that gets
missed in this discussion is that while
Canadian real estate has been a rocket
over this period, so has the stock
market. Let me give you some data to set
the stage, and then I'll explain my
model. The average 20-year annualized
return on the price of apartments for
the 12 cities in my sample is 5.11%.
It was higher in some cities and lower
in others. That may not seem like a huge
number, but over 20 years it leads to
substantial price appreciation. For
example, an average apartment in Toronto
cost $198,300
in January 2005 and $62,700
in December 2024. That's an annualized
return of 5.74%.
Compound growth can accomplish a lot
given a long enough time, even with a
modest return. Don't get me wrong, that
real estate return is pretty good. But a
portfolio consisting of 30% Canadian
stock index and 70% global stock index
returned an annualized 8.62% over the
same period. That would have turned
$198,300
into more than $1 million. Those numbers
don't tell the full story because the
renter had to pay rent and the owner had
other costs associated with living in
and maintaining their home. But these
numbers do put the price returns of real
estate into perspective. They have been
high, but probably not as high as many
people imagine when they think about the
Canadian real estate market relative to
other assets. The highest annualized
price return in my sample was Kitchener
Waterlue at 6.99% followed by Vancouver
at 6.45%.
Some other cities had much lower
appreciation over this period which
points to an interesting observation.
There's a ton of dispersion in real
estate markets across the country. The
last thing I want to mention about the
data before I get into describing the
rent versus own model is that the end of
my sample period saw sharp price
declines for some cities while stocks
were resilient. Toronto, for example,
saw apartment prices fall 21% from March
2022 through December 2024, affecting
the rent versus own results. Okay, let
me describe the model. In January 2005,
you're renting a place to live, paying
the average apartment rent in one of the
12 cities in my sample. You've saved up
enough cash for a 20% down payment and
closing costs based on the average cost
of buying an apartment in that city and
you're trying to decide whether you
really want to buy a place or keep
renting and invest that cash in the
stock market. I'm using apartments
because the data for single family home
rentals are more sparse, which does
speak to one of the reasons that buying
can make sense. There aren't a ton of
single family homes available for rent.
If that's what you want, renting simply
may not be an option. That being said,
my last rental before I bought a home
was a beautiful detached home in a great
part of Ottawa at a great rental price.
So, those rentals are out there if
you're lucky. Anyway, I'm using
apartment data for this analysis due to
its availability and quality. Okay, so
we're in January 2005, sitting on some
cash and deciding whether to keep
renting or to buy an apartment. The
model tracks the counterfactual outcomes
through the net worth of the two
scenarios over time. If you keep
renting, the cash you had saved up gets
invested in stocks. And if you buy, the
cash goes toward purchasing the
apartment. In the model, the homeowner
has enough cash flow to cover the cost
of owning, including property taxes,
maintenance costs, including condo fees
or strata fees, insurance, and the
mortgage payment. The mortgage is
financed with 20% down and a 25-year
mortgage at the prevailing mortgage rate
at the time. The renter has the exact
same amount of cash flow available, but
they typically have lower monthly cash
flow costs since they're only paying
rent and a lower amount for insurance.
The monthly difference between the
owners and the renters's cash flow costs
is invested in the renters's portfolio
if it's positive and withdrawn from the
portfolio if it's negative. Keep in mind
though that the owner's cash flow costs
are much higher than just the mortgage
payment. This savings assumption is one
of the biggest assumptions in my model,
so it's worth spending a minute on.
Forced savings is one of the best
arguments for buying a home. If you're
going to rent and spend instead of rent
and save, you're likely better off
buying a place to live. Those big
mortgage payments contain a significant
amount of principal repayment, which is
building equity in the home by reducing
the amount that you owe. That is a great
feature of mortgage debt if you don't
trust your ability to be a disciplined
saver as a renter. However, a
disciplined renter, as we're about to
see, has at least an equal opportunity
to accumulate wealth. The renters's
portfolio in the model consists of 30%
Canadian equity and 70% global equity
index funds with an annual fee of 0.25%.
It's similar to BEQT. In my analysis,
rent does increase every year. That's
one of the most common questions I get
about this type of analysis based on the
historical rent increase in each city.
The rent increases over this period are
6.24% per year on average. And I do find
that over the full period, owning tends
to look better than renting in cities
with the fastest rent growth. This makes
sense. One of the best financial
arguments for owning is that it hedges
the cost of living in that specific
home. And that hedge did pay off in my
analysis. Let's look at Toronto as an
example. In January 2005, you're sitting
on $43,626
and paying $973 per month in rent. You
consider buying a condo worth $198,300
requiring a $39,660
down payment and a loan of $158,640.
Mortgage rates at the time are 4.1%
resulting in a mortgage payment of $843
per month. I think right here is where a
lot of people get stuck. They see that
rent costs more than the mortgage
payment and believe that renting is just
throwing money away. But the owner also
has property tax of $282 per month and
maintenance costs, including condo fees,
of $324 per month. This leaves $476 per
month in additional monthly costs that
the owner needs to cover in excess of
the cost of renting. Holding available
cash flows constant, that monthly amount
can be invested by the renter. The
monthly savings amount does decrease
over time in this Toronto example and
even becomes negative by January 2022 as
the mortgage payment stays fairly stable
over time while rent increases. Rent in
2022 in the model is just under $2,000
per month in Toronto. That seems like it
would make the owner come out ahead. But
by this point, the renter has an
investment portfolio worth $340,000.
and the portfolio's return in a typical
month far exceeds the difference in cash
flow costs, allowing the renter to
continue accumulating wealth. This is a
good place to dispel another common
argument that renters will always pay
the owner's cash flow costs plus a
profit margin for the landlord. I'm
sorry to tell you, but that's not how a
market works. Market rents are not set
by landlords based on what their cash
flow costs are. It is not uncommon for
landlords to be eating monthly cash flow
shortfalls on their rentals. Increasing
the price of rent only works if people
are willing to pay rent at that price.
And in a competitive market, that will
not always be the case. Okay, for the 12
cities that I looked at, seven favored
renting and five favored owning over the
full period January 2005 through
December 2024, measured by the ending
net worth of the renter relative to the
owner. The simple average of the ending
wealth ratio of renters to owners is
1.17.
Meaning the renters on average had 1.17
times the wealth of owners. To make sure
it's clear, when the renter to owner
wealth ratio is above one, renters came
out ahead. And when it is below one,
owners came out ahead. Owning does look
better in places that you would expect
like Vancouver, Kitchener, Waterlue, and
Victoria. And in some surprising places
like Calgary and Edmonton, Montreal,
Ottawa, Winnipeg, Quebec City, Hamilton,
and Halifax all favored renters, as did,
to my surprise, Toronto. Let's look at
each one in a bit of detail quickly.
Keep in mind that these charts reflect
the effects of both the renters and
owners housing costs over time. Toronto
was a close outcome with an ending
wealth ratio of 1.05.
Rents and prices increased a lot over
the full period, but the cost of renting
was not terribly high relative to the
cost of owning. The renter and owner had
similar wealth with a few lead changes
until 2015 when real estate prices took
off. But then they came back down after
2022, while the broadly diversified
stock portfolio maintained its value.
Montreal favored renting for most of the
period and had an ending wealth ratio of
1.48. Rent growth and the cost of
renting relative to the cost of owning
were fairly low over this period,
allowing renters to stay ahead. Price
growth was also modest for real estate
here. Vancouver was rough for renters to
nobody's surprise over most of the
period with an ending wealth ratio of
0.71.
Rents were not terribly high relative to
the cost of owning, but the high price
growth and rapidly rising rents made it
difficult for a renter to keep up. Even
still, a wealth ratio of 0.71 is
probably not as bad as people imagine
when they think about renters in
Vancouver over the last 20 years.
Calgary and Edmonton are two of the most
interesting cases. They had very low
price returns from most of the sample,
but a big jump in prices early on. The
result is that the owner comes out way
ahead of the renter. Rents were also
high relative to the cost of owning,
making it difficult for renters to save.
Renting does come out ahead in three of
the four 5-year sub periods, but due to
that initial price jump, these two
cities have the worst rent to own wealth
ratios in the sample at 0.37 and 0.39.
Ottawa is another one that I found
surprising. The wealth ratio is 1.97 at
the end of the period due to modest
price growth for real estate and fairly
low rents relative to the cost of
owning. Winnipeg had low price returns
and fairly high cash flow costs for
owners relative to renters, allowing
renters to accumulate significantly more
wealth with an ending wealth ratio of
2.93.
Quebec City and Hamilton saw mixed
results and had multiple lead changes
throughout the analysis, but renters
came out ahead at the end of the period
with wealth ratios of 1.14 and 1.12.
Kitchener, Waterlue and Victoria both
had strong price returns that allowed
owners to stay ahead of renters for most
of the sample with ending wealth ratios
of 0.71 and 0.85
and Halifax had multiple lead changes
but ultimately favored renters with a
finishing wealth ratio of 1.26. That
full period analysis is interesting, but
I'm guessing that many of you watching
didn't buy a place 20 years ago and
continue living there until today. To
address that, I also look at the four
non-over overlapping 5-year sub periods.
The sub periods are modeling the same
rent versus owned decision I described
earlier except the decision is being
made in January 2005, 2010, 2015, and
2020. And then the result is being
examined 5 years into the future in each
case. There's no magic to the 5-year
number other than it giving me four
equal length sub periods to examine.
Moving to sub periods changes the
results quite a bit. While real estate
prices increased over the full period,
they were relatively flat or even
negative over some sub periods for some
cities. The other big difference with
the sub periods is that the cash flow
cost of taking out a mortgage at higher
prices later in the sample requires
higher cash flows from the owner in the
model, allowing the renter to save more.
For example, owning a place that you
bought in 2005 will tend to have lower
cash flow costs than renting at today's
rent prices. But buying a place today
would likely cost more than renting when
all cash flow costs are considered. In
the 2005 to 2009 sub period, owning
comes at a head in most cities. Renting
only fared better in Montreal, Ottawa,
Hamilton, and Halifax. Over the 2010 to
2014 sub period, renting comes out ahead
everywhere, largely due to low real
estate price returns over the period,
which averaged 2.43% annualized. 2015 to
2019 was mixed with five cities favoring
owning. And the 2020 to 2024 period
favors renting everywhere except
Halifax, largely due to the fact that
real estate prices fell in many cities
over this period. While the stock market
soared over all 48 sub periods across 12
cities, I find that renting comes out
ahead 71% of the time. These findings
are in line with past research on this
topic. For US real estate, the 2012
paper, Lessons from over 30 years of buy
versus rent decisions. Is the American
dream always wise? finds that over the
period 1978 to 2009, renting beats
owning 75% of the time for eight-year
holding periods when the renter invests
in a portfolio of stocks and bonds
matched to the risk of the relevant real
estate market. For Canadian real estate,
the 2007 paper are renters being left
behind finds that renter wealth matched
or exceeded owner wealth in seven of the
nine cities studied over the period 1979
to 2006 when the renter invests in a
Canadian index fund. I find these data
compelling. To be clear, they're not
saying that renting is financially
superior to owning, though they do seem
to show a bit of an edge on average. The
data do show that renters have a fair
shake at matching the wealth
accumulation of owners. That doesn't
mean that they actually will match the
wealth of owners because saving and
investing can be behaviorally
challenging, but it seems overly
paternalistic to me to turn that into a
prescription that everyone must buy a
home. If someone is confident in their
ability to save and invest while
renting, it's not necessarily true that
they are at a financial disadvantage
relative to an owner. These data support
that. Okay, this next bit is going to
get nerdy. I'm going to walk through my
assumptions and data sources in more
detail. I will also go through some
sensitivity analysis to show how things
like high investment fees and a lack of
discipline in saving can affect
outcomes. Data for rents in the model
are from the CMHC rental market survey.
The data are updated as of October of
each year. I match the October survey
data to each respective year in the
model. Meaning that for example, January
2005 rents are based on the October 2005
rental survey data. Survey rents
represent the weighted average of both
vacant and occupied units. I use a unit
weighted average of primary and
secondary market rents to come up with a
rental cost assumption in each market.
The renter in the model invests an
initial lump sum and then saves or
withdraws the difference between their
cash flow costs and the owner's costs
into an investment portfolio. The gross
of fees return on the renters's
portfolio over the full sample period is
8.62%
and I net out a 0.25% fee. The portfolio
in the model is not taxed representative
of the renter using FHSA, RRSP and TFSA
accounts as they became available
throughout the sample period. Based on
the amounts being saved, I think it
would be feasible for the renter to use
their registered accounts for the full
simulation. If we did introduce taxes on
investments, it would make owning a home
increasingly attractive at increasing
personal income tax rates. The tax-free
growth of the primary residence is a
major advantage for Canadians who have
maxed out their registered accounts.
Home price data come from the MLS home
price index apartment benchmark for each
city. These data do not reflect any
repair, renovation, or maintenance
spending from homeowners that
contributes to index returns. I account
for these in the model by applying 1%
depreciation to the index annually and
having the owner spend 1/3 of the
renters's rent payment on maintenance
and repairs. I tested this maintenance
cost assumption against the actual cost
of current condo fees in each market, a
cost that forms a big part of
maintenance spending for a condo, and
found that the numbers match up really
well. Maintenance and depreciation is a
big assumption and often a point of
contention in this type of analysis. So,
let me provide some additional color. To
understand the net capital returns
occurring to homeowners, we need to
adjust the gross market appreciation of
something like the HPI index for
depreciation, maintenance, and
renovation costs. This is important
particularly in a rent versus zone
comparison because rents reflect similar
costs incurred by landlords. To make it
a fair comparison, the costs need to be
accounted for on the owner's side, too.
Quantifying these items is not so easy.
Academic Research that I'll link in the
description finds a value between 2 and
3% as a reasonable assumption. In
National Accounts Data, Statistics
Canada reports average maintenance and
repair costs over the sample period of
0.82% as a proportion of net residential
housing stock and renovation spending of
2.48%.
This implies that there's something
around a 3.3% average annual
contribution to home values that can be
attributed to costs incurred by
homeowners across the 12 cities. My
average combined maintenance and
depreciation assumption is 2.66% which
is in line with academic research and
Statistics Canada data. A common
argument here is that people can DIY
their home repairs and upgrades. I would
say that doing that work instead of some
other work is implicitly costing it. For
example, if I had painted my house
instead of making this video, the
economic cost of painting my house would
be huge, even if I didn't pay anything
out of pocket. There's also a good
chance those DIY projects are costing
you more than you realize. I have
watched seasoned trades people undo DIY
work in order to do it properly, and
it's often a lot harder and more costly
than if done properly to begin with. For
financing, the owner in the model takes
out a 25-year mortgage on a 5-year fixed
term at the prevailing mortgage rate at
that time. For the full period analysis,
the mortgage is renewed every 5 years at
the relevant mortgage rates. Property
tax rates are based on the historical
property tax rates for each city. These
were handcolcted from municipal websites
or by contacting the municipality if it
was not available online. Transaction
costs the model are 2% of the value of
the property at purchase and 6% at sale.
This includes things like real estate
commissions, legal costs, and other
things like staging costs. Changing some
of these assumptions can make a big
difference. For example, if I set
investment fees to 1%, common for an
actively managed fund instead of the
0.25%
representative of an index fund, the
average renter to owner wealth ratio
drops to 1.02 at the end of the sample.
Accounting for the behavior of investors
who often buy stocks when they're high
and either sell or stop buying when
they're low could have a similar or even
more severe effect. If the renter saves
80% of the cash flow cost difference
between renting and owning instead of
100% the average wealth ratio drops to
0.93.
The sensitivity of the results to those
assumptions and the fact that many
Canadians do have low financial literacy
and do invest in high fee actively
managed mutual funds or individual
stocks does make me think that owning a
home may make sense for a lot of people.
It's probably easier for many people to
buy a home and make their mortgage
payments than it is for them to be
disciplined savers, build a lowcost
diversified portfolio of stocks, and
stick with their investments through
good times and bad. However, you finance
nerds watching this 20inut admittedly
technical video on renting versus zoning
are not most people. Thanks for
watching. I'm Ben Felix, chief
investment officer at PWL Capital. If
you are struggling with a rent versus
own decision for housing in Canada, the
financial planners at PWL Capital can
help. You can book a meeting with us
below.